Louis N. Ridenour Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Louis N. Ridenour Papers 1917-1960 (bulk 1945-1959)
MSS83966
Ridenour, Louis N. (Louis Nicot), 1911-1959
1,300 items
9 containers
3.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Physicist and author. Correspondence, journals, reports, writings, printed matter, photographs, and other items relating to science policy issues concerning nuclear energy and computer technology as well as Ridenour's contribution to the development and application of radar technology during World War II.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Alsop, Joseph, 1910-1989--Correspondence.; Baker, Cary F.--Correspondence.; Benjamin, Curtis G., 1901-1983--Correspondence.; Bennett, Ralph D.--Correspondence.; Bowden, B. Vivian--Correspondence.; Bowles, Edward Lindley, 1897-1990--Correspondence.; Bryson, Lyman, 1888-1959--Correspondence.; Cousins, Norman--Correspondence.; Davison, Peter, 1926- --Correspondence.; Flanagan, Dennis, 1919-2005--Correspondence.; Handsfield, Hugh, 1911- --Correspondence.; Haydn, Hiram Collins, 1907-1973--Correspondence.; Ledgerwood, Byron K.--Correspondence.; Lessing, Lawrence--Correspondence.; Levin, Lawrence Meyer, 1898-1968--Correspondence.; Maurer, Herrymon, 1914-1998--Correspondence.; Morton, Charles W., 1899-1967--Correspondence.; Muste, A. J. (Abraham John), 1885-1967--Correspondence.; Nagel, Carl E.--Correspondence.; Nelson, Oliver A.--Correspondence.; Paterson, Isabel, 1886-1961--Correspondence.; Piel, Gerard--Correspondence.; Reid, James M.--Correspondence.; Ridenour, Louis N. (Louis Nicot), 1911-1959.; Shinohara, Kenʼichi, 1905- --Correspondence.; Solow, Herbert, 1903-1964--Correspondence.; Spaatz, Carl, 1891-1974.; Svirsky, Leon, 1904-1974--Correspondence.; Tovrov, Orin--Correspondence.; Weeks, Edward, 1898-1989--Correspondence.; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975--Correspondence.; Wylie, Philip, 1902-1971--Correspondence.
Organizations
Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Radiation Laboratory.; United States Strategic Air Forces in Europe.; United States. War Department.
Subjects
Antiaircraft guns.; Computers.; Nuclear energy--Government policy--United States.; Radar in aeronautics.; Radar.; Science and state--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations, American.; World War, 1939-1945--Antiaircraft artillery operations.; World War, 1939-1945--Radar.
Occupations
Authors.; Physicists.
Provenance
The papers of Louis N. Ridenour, physicist and author, were given to the Library of Congress by his daughters, Nancy Ridenour Buchanan and Eleanor Ridenour Crow, in 1997.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Louis N. Ridenour are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1911, Nov. 11 Born, Montclair, N. J.
1932 B.S. in physics, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1934 Married Gretchen Hinckley Kraemer
1936 1938 Instructor in physics, Princeton University, Princeton, N.J.
1938 Ph.D. in physics, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, Calif.
1938 1941 Professor of Physics, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa.
1941 1944 Assistant director, Radiation Laboratory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Boston, Mass.; headed team that developed SCR 584 gun laying radar
1942 1946 Consultant to the secretary of war; field duty as chief radar advisor in North African, European, and Pacific theaters of World War II
1947 1951 Professor of physics and dean of graduate college, University of Illinois, Urbana, Ill. Editor-in-chief, Radiation Laboratory series of technical books
1948 1952 Chairman, scientific advisory board to the chief of staff, United States Air Force
1951 1954 Vice president, International Telemeter Corp., Los Angeles, Calif.
1952 1953 Visiting professor of engineering, University of California, Los Angeles, Calif.
1954 Published and edited with William A. Nierenberg, Modern Physics for the Engineer (New York: McGraw-Hill. 2 vols.)
1955 Director of program development, Missile System Division, Lockheed Aircraft Corp., Burbank, Calif.
1955 1957 Director of research, Missile System Division, Lockheed Aircraft Corp., Burbank, Calif.
1957 1959 Assistant general manager and chief scientist, Lockheed Aircraft Corp., Burbank, Calif.
1959 Vice president and general manager, Electronics and Avionics Division, Lockheed Aircraft Corp., Burbank Calif.
1959, May 21 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the physicist Louis Nicot Ridenour (1911-1959) span the years 1917-1960, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the postwar period, 1945-1959. The collection includes correspondence, draft and published writings, photographs, journals, reports, scientific papers, and printed matter arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Ridenour led the team at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology Radiation Laboratory that in the early 1940s developed the SCR 584, a radar device that was key to the first effective gun laying antiaircraft system. During 1944-1945 while chief of the Advisory Specialist Group of the United States Strategic Air Forces in Europe commanded by Carl Spaatz, Ridenour adapted the SCR 584 to the close control of Allied fighter bombers in foul weather. He pioneered the development of airborne radar and radar controlled bomb sights. Journals from the World War II service file in the collection are a daily record of Ridenour's activities in the European and North African theaters of air operations.
In the postwar period Ridenour endeavored to familiarize the general public with the science and policy issues related to the new technology of atomic weapons and digital computers by writing for publications such as Atlantic Monthly, Fortune, Saturday Review of Literature, Scientific American, and in preparing numerous encyclopedia articles. He also sought to reach other scientists and technologists, especially engineers, through articles in specialist publications and by editing and cowriting books such as Modern Physics for the Engineer and Radar Systems Engineering.
These papers mainly document the writing and editing phase of Ridenour's career. Some of Ridenour's early fiction from his high school and college days and his correspondence as the editor of the University of Chicago's Daily Maroon is included in the early education file. Ridenour's long-term writing projects and consultant relationship with publishers generated a substantial correspondence with editors, coauthors, sources, and readers. Notable correspondents represented in the speeches and writing file include Lyman Bryson, Norman Cousins, Peter H. Davison, Dennis Flanagan, Hiram Haydn, Byron K. Ledgerwood, Larry Lessing, Lawrence M. Levin, Herrymon Maurer, Charles W. Morton, A. J. Muste, Oliver A. Nelson, Isabel Paterson, Gerard Piel, Herbert Solow, and Edward Weeks.
Ridenour's writing and editorial activities also occasioned many letters in the general correspondence. Editors, publishers, and writers not previously listed include Joseph Alsop, Cary F. Baker, Curtis G. Benjamin, Hugh H. Handsfield, Carl G. Nagel, James M. Reid, Leon Svirsky, Orin Tovrov, Thornton Wilder, and Philip Wylie. Scientist with whom Ridenour corresponded include Ralph D. Bennett, Edward L. Bowles, B. Vivian Bowden, and Kenʼichi Shinohara.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material.
Container List
- Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Death of Ridenour, 1959-1971, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellany, 1928-1957, undated (Box 1)
- Book binding, 1954-1958 (Box 1)
- Buchanan, Nancy Ridenour (daughter), 1982-1987, undated (Box 1)
- Brookhaven National Laboratory, Camp Upton, N.Y. (Box 1)
- Clippings, 1947-1959, undated (Box 1)
- Douglas Aircraft Co. (Box 1)
  - Miscellany, 1945-1948, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Project Rand, 1947-1950, undated (Box 1)
- Early education (Box 1)
  - Miscellany, 1917-1931, (1 folder) (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Student newspapers (Box 2)
    - Daily Maroon, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill., 1931-1932, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Miscellany, 1923-1926, undated (Box 2)
- General correspondence (Box 2)
  - 1931-1954, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1955-1959, (4 folders) (Box 3)
- Institute of Radio Engineers, 1953-1956 (Box 3)
- International Telemeter Corp. (Box 3)
  - Clippinger, Richard F., 1952, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellany, 1952-1954, undated (Box 3)
- Job offers, 1941-1948, undated (Box 4)
- Lockheed Aircraft Corp. (Box 4)
  - Miscellany, 1956-1958, undated (Box 4)
  - Proposal for the creation of Lockheed Electronics and Avionics Division (LEAD), 1959, (3 folders) (Box 4)
- Manuals (Box 4)
  - Analytical Differentiation by a Digital Computer, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Compiler A-2, 1953 (Box 4)
- Photographs, 1922-1960, undated, (1 folder) (Box 4, Box 5)
- Printed matter, 1945-1959, (2 folders) (Box 5)
- Scientific Advisory Board, United States Air Force (Box 5)
  - Project Lincoln and the Beacon Hill Study Group, 1951-1952 (Box 5)
  - Project Vista, 1951-1952 (Box 5)
  - Research and Development in the United States Air Force, (Ridenour Report), 1949 (Box 5)
- Scrapbook, 1935, undated (Box 5)
- Speeches and writings (Box 5)
  - Articles and book chapters (Box 5)
    - American Peoples Encyclopedia, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Atlantic Monthly, 1946-1957, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Book of Science, Grolier Society, 1946, undated (Box 6)
    - Collier's Encyclopedia, 1952-1959, undated (Box 6)
    - Control Engineering, 1955, undated (Box 6)
    - Electronics, 1954 (Box 6)
    - Encyclopedia Americana, 1947-1954 (Box 6)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1945-1957 (Box 6)
    - Fortune, 1946-1956, undated (Box 6)
    - Look, 1952-1955 (Box 6)
    - Miscellany (Box 6)
      - Drafts, 1946, n.d (Box 6)
      - Published articles, 1945-1958, undated, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 6, Box 7)
    - An Outline of Man's Knowledge, 1957-1959, undated (Box 7)
    - Saturday Review of Literature, 1946-1959, undated (Box 7)
    - Scientific American, 1951-1956, undated (Box 7)
    - Tele-Tech, 1951-1952, undated (Box 7)
    - World Book Encyclopedia, 1957, undated (Box 7)
    - Virginia Quarterly Review, 1954-1959, undated (Box 7)
  - Books (Box 8)
    - McGraw-Hill handbook series, 1953-1957, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Modern Physics for the Engineer (Box 8)
      - Miscellany, 1952-1958, (2 folders) (Box 8)
      - Permissions, 1953-1954 (Box 8)
    - Radar Systems Engineering, 1956-1959, undated (Box 8)
    - Unidentified work, undated (Box 8)
  - Fiction (Box 8)
    - Miscellany, 1934-1947, n.d (Box 8)
    - Pilot Light of the Apocalypse, 1945-1957, undated (Box 8)
  - Scientific papers (Box 9)
    - "Artificial Radioactivity Produced by Alpha-Particles," Physical Review, 1937 (Box 9)
    - Miscellany (Box 9)
      - Drafts with related data, 1934-1947, undated (Box 9)
      - Published papers, 1931-1949 (Box 9)
  - Speeches and statements (Box 9)
    - Miscellany, 1946-1948, undated (Box 9)
    - Mutual Insurance Co., Chicago, Ill., two hundredth anniversary, 1951-1952, undated (Box 9)
- World War II service (Box 9)
  - Journals, 1942-1945 (Box 9)
  - Miscellany, 1942-1946 (Box 9)